Because I have realized
是因为我已经知道了
That opposition is futile
反对没有用
Excessive compliance can lead to an organizational inertia of silence
过度顺从会导致一个惯性的组织沉默
Which could very likely accelerate decline
很有可能加速衰老
If you oppose it
反对的话
A good outcome is the only true result
好的结果才叫结果
An unfavorable outcome is the cost
不好的结果叫代价
If I ask you to spend 5000 on a Spring Festival Gala
让你花5000办个春晚
Do you oppose this?
这东西你反不反对这个东西
Before there's an objective outcome
没有一个客观的结果之前
I don't think anyone can predict it in advance
我不认为大家是能提早预判的
This is a matter of being wise or foolish
你这是愚蠢与否的
Don't bring up any grand ideals with me right now.
你这时候不用跟我提什么宏伟的远大理想
I'm struggling with my current predicament
我眼前的苟且我都过不过去
I now believe that the brave ones are the first to embrace the world
我现在觉得勇敢的人先接受世界
Critical thinking knows no bounds
思辨不设限
Welcome to our casual space
欢迎来随便
Welcome everyone to the 'Casual or Not' show, brought to you by Bilibili
欢迎大家来到我们B站推出的随便不随便节目
I'm the host for today.
我是今天的主持人
In the workplace, what I like most is the salary
职场上我最喜欢的是工资啊
What I fear the most is my boss
我最害怕的是老板
Worse than a boss is a boss who has lost it
比老板更可怕的是疯掉的老板
When we encounter a boss
当我们一旦遇到老板
Some opinions might not be very wise
有些意见可能不太明智
It might seem a bit crazy
可能有些发疯
or even a bit foolish I don’t know how everyone would choose some might opt for silence as a virtue enduring for a calm and peaceful outcome while others might step up
甚至可能有些愚蠢 我不知道大家会怎么选择 有些人可能会选择沉默是金啊 忍一个风平浪静 有些人呢有可能就会选择挺身而出啊
for the sake of truth
来一个真理
the more we debate, the clearer it becomes
越辩越明
this is today’s debate topic
这就是咱们今天的辩题
the boss’s foolish decision
叫做老板的愚蠢决策
Should I comply or oppose?
我应该顺从还是反对
First, let me invite our debaters from both sides.
首先啊我来邀请一下我们正反双方的选手
Proponent Zhang Eerda
正方张尔达
Opponent representative, psychology expert, and commentator Lao Jiang, who is extremely reliable
反方代表心理学愉悦点评嘉宾老蒋巨靠谱
Now, let's move on to our formal casual debate segment.
接下来就进入到我们正式的随便不随便环节
The casual debate is divided into
随便不随便共分
Casual argumentation
随便立论
Soul-searching questions
灵魂发问
High-energy rebuttals
高能开杠
Rebuttal summary
开杠小结
Let's wrap it up casually.
随便总结
We have six casual segments for everyone.
全体随便六个环节
Next, I will announce the rules for being casual or not.
接下来我宣布随便不随便
The third debate session is now officially starting.
第三场辩论赛现在正式开始
First, we have the casual opening statement round.
首先呢就是我们的随便立论环节
Each side has four minutes to present their opening arguments.
正反双方各有4分钟的时间来展开立论
Let's start with the affirmative team.
首先把时间交给正方
Hello, everyone.
大家好
I need to put on my armor first.
我要先叠甲
I am the deputy head of a media company.
我是一个传媒公司的二把手
This question suits me well. It's because I'm the closest to the boss, the closest to foolishness, and the closest to making decisions. And for this debate, I'm on the affirmative side. It's because I can only be on the affirmative side.
这个题很适合我 是因为我是距离老板 距离愚蠢 距离决策都最近的人 以及这个题我站正方 是因为我只能站正方
If I chose to oppose,
如果我选择反对的话
I wouldn't be able to take the day off today,
今天这个假请不出来
and I might not be able to be here.
我可能不能来到现场
The boss's foolish decision,
老板的愚蠢决定呢
I used to oppose it frequently as well.
以前我也经常反对的
Most of the time, the result is just four words.
大部分结果就是四个字
Totally useless.
毛用没有
I believe all employees have heard this line:
我相信所有打工人都听过一句话
It goes, 'I have a little idea.'
叫做我有一个小想法
I have no idea how this became a nationwide standard.
我都不知道这个是怎么做到全国统一的
Today, we're going live to sell products.
今天要搞直播带货
Tomorrow, we're diving into cross-border e-commerce.
明天要搞跨境电商
These are the little tricks in the boss's mind.
老板脑子里的小花招
Gulp, gulp, gulp.
咕咚咕咚咕咚啊
It's the same as what we get wholesale from Yiwu
跟义乌批发的一样
He feels ideas bubbling up every day
他每天觉得自己咕咚咕咚思如泉涌
Can we stop the gushing spring?
我们挡得住泉涌吗
This goes against nature
这个违背大自然啊
The key is to stop the gushing spring
关键我们要去挡泉涌
What do we want to do?
我们想干嘛呢
I initially thought it was simple
我一开始想的很简单
To prevent the water from splashing onto me
为了不要让水溅到我自己身上嘛
But I put in a lot of effort
但是我费很大劲儿
I managed to block the spring source
我把这个泉眼给堵死
Is he not going to move underground anymore?
难道他这个地下就不活动了吗
I blocked the spring.
我把这泉眼堵死了
I was just feeling happy.
我正高兴呢
Hehe, it poisoned me.
嘿嘿毒死我
I turned around and saw
一回头一看
the volcano erupted.
火山喷发了
The spring is gone.
泉水没有了
The lava is coming. It's even worse than the spring. So my first thought was that it's unstoppable. Ideas flow like a spring Let's not get in the way When the flood comes It's best to learn how to swim Nothing beats that
岩浆来了 还不如泉水 所以我的第一个想法就是挡不住的 思如泉涌 我们就不要挡了 发大水的时候 自己学会游泳 比什么都强
Especially in the Yangtze River Delta region
尤其是我们在长三角地区啊
Free shipping in Jiangsu, Zhejiang, and Shanghai
江浙沪包邮
After all, we need to learn this
我们毕竟要学会的
This is my first idea
这个是我的第一个想法
My second thought is about a noon one day
第二个想法呢是我有一天正午的
That was a minor incident when I just started working.
那个是我刚刚上班很小的一件事情
We are closely connected to the domestic entertainment industry.
我们是和内娱紧密相连的一个工作
I've thought about it countless nights.
无数个夜里我都想到了
One year, we organized an event at Taihu Bay.
有一年我们在太湖湾办活动
An artist told me at the time,
当时呢有一个艺人他跟我说
He insisted on staying in a sea-view room.
他一定要住海景房
I told him this is Changzhou.
我说这里是常州
Where's the sea?
哪里来的海
He said he didn't care.
他说那我不管的
I'm not a big star anymore.
我现在不是个大牌
It's also a mid-range brand
也是个中牌
Now, for all my events, I only stay in ocean-view rooms
我现在所有的活动全部都要住海景房
I got really upset at that time
我当时我就生气
Whether it's a big brand or a small one
什么大牌小牌子
Men's and women's volleyball
男排女排
Have some chicken cutlets
你吃点鸡排吧
Call my boss for me
你我给我老板打电话
I said, take a look
我说你看看
Support me
你给我撑腰
What I mean
我的意思
But my boss said to arrange a sea-view room for him
但我老板说给他安排海景房
He wants a sea-view room
他要海景房
So find him a sea-view room
你就给他找海景房
I thought it was ridiculous at the time
我当时觉得太蠢了
He lacks geographical knowledge
他没有地理常识
Do you lack it too?
你也没有吗
I got angry I said I wouldn't handle this matter You figure it out yourself Turns out, in the afternoon, our boss did post a message in the group He said he found you the nearest sea-view room, brother.
我就生气了 我说我我不处理了这个事情 你自己想办法吧 结果下午确实是我们老板在群里发了一段话 他说兄弟给你找到了最近的海景房
The scenery is beautiful.
风景优美
It's 240 kilometers away from here.
距离这里240km
The drive takes about three hours.
车程大概三个小时
So we'll pick you up at four in the morning on the day of the event.
所以活动当天我们会在早上四点钟来接你
Please make sure to set an alarm for 3:30 AM to wake up.
请你务必定一个半夜03:30起床的闹钟
If you want to get a good rest,
如果想要好好休息的话
we've also prepared a lake-view room for you.
我们还为你准备了湖景房
I can get you a couple of large hairy crabs as well.
我再给你弄两只大闸蟹
All the artists for this event are staying at this hotel.
我们这次活动的艺人全部住在这个酒店
You have the chance to have a good conversation.
你们有机会可以好好交流
Take a look and see which one you want to choose.
你看看你想选哪个
I saw this text in the group at that time.
我当时看到群里这个文字
I felt so foolish myself.
我觉得我自己好蠢
Back then, I was just starting my internship.
那个时候我刚实习
I felt like I only saw the surface right and wrong.
我觉得我只看到了表面的对与错
I was still struggling with the geographical facts.
我还在纠结那里地理常识
But the essence of cooperation is the exchange of benefits.
但是合作的本质是利益交换
The fact that he could bring up this foolish idea means that
他能提出这个蠢A就代表
The foolish idea is what he cares about the most.
蠢A是他最在意的东西
I thought Stupid A was a sea-view room
我以为蠢A是海景房
But Stupid A is his pride
但蠢A是他的面子
When you oppose Stupid A, you're opposing his pride
你反对蠢A反对的是他的面子
So no matter how stupid Stupid A seems to me I have to go along with it Even if we bring up a Wise B to counter Stupid A He still has to be an option on the table After this little incident I suddenly realized something very important
所以无论蠢A在我眼里多蠢 都得顺下去 即使拿出一个睿智B蠢A 他也依然得是桌面上的选项 经过这个小插曲呢 突然我就意识到一件非常重要的事情
I finally got it
就是我就反应过来
It seems like 99% of the company's decisions have nothing to do with me
好像公司99%的决策跟我没什么关系
I just have to do 99% of the work no matter what
我只是无论如何都要干99%的事情
and carry 99% of the burden
背99%的锅
only to receive a measly 9.9 yuan bonus
领个九块九的奖金
and end up getting food poisoning from the cheap meals
吃点拼好饭中毒
Since we have to push through anyway
既然横竖都得推进哈
I'll happily execute the smart decisions
聪明的决定我就开开心心的做
the stupid ones
愚蠢的决定
I'll grumble and moan while doing them
我就骂骂咧咧地做
there's no point in putting up more resistance
没有必要多一轮抵抗
Loving others can be exhausting.
我们爱人很累的
We need to learn how to conserve our energy.
要学会给自己节能
Ideas flow like a spring.
思如泉涌
Seek out opportunities.
寻找机会
That’s a key trait of a boss.
本来就是老板的主要品质
When this trait is applied in the right context,
这个品质用对地方的时候
We feel it’s a quality that leads to success, not otherwise.
我们觉得是成功品质没用
At the right time,
对的时候
Do we think it’s foolish?
我们觉得愚蠢吗
But this is a Schrödinger’s quality.
但这个是薛定谔的品质
We didn't know until things were settled.
事情落地之前我们也不知道
So I came out to work.
所以出来打工
I don't care about the money.
我不惦记钱
I'm always thinking about the boss's decisions.
我成天惦记老板的决策
Whether it's smart or not,
愚不愚蠢
it makes me look a bit foolish.
就会显得我有点愚蠢
No matter how foolish it is,
不管蠢不蠢
things need to move forward.
事情都是要推进的
As long as I get what I deserve,
那我觉得只要我能拿到我应得的钱
the core interests remain unchanged.
核心利益不变
Other trivial matters
其他无关紧要
This is my current survival strategy in the workplace Thank you all Thank you, Teacher Erdar, for sharing your workplace experience with us. I feel like I've gained another survival skill I've even learned how to find a sea view room in Taihu
这个是我目前的职场生存之道 谢谢大家 感谢尔达老师给我们分享的职场经验 我觉得我保命的技能又加了一条 甚至学会了在太湖找海景房
Next, let's welcome Teacher Yueyue from the opposing side
那么接下来我们就有请反方愉悦老师
To start your argument
来开始您的立论
Let's first clarify a few concepts and definitions
那我们先来做几个概念跟定义的辨析啊
First, who gets to decide what's foolish
就首先这愚蠢是谁来判断的
First, the boss definitely doesn't think they're stupid.
首先呢就是老板肯定不会认为自己蠢啊
Even if they do think so,
即便是他认为自己蠢
they won't say it out loud.
但也不会说出来
So, it's up to the employees to judge.
那只能员工来判断
When it comes to macro strategies,
那宏观策略方面
as Professor Zhang mentioned earlier,
就像刚才张老师提到的
most employees are beyond your control,
多数员工你是管不着的啊
they don't fall under your jurisdiction,
也不归你管
and you shouldn't even try to manage them.
你也别想管
The only area you have decision-making power over is the daily execution level.
那只有日常执行层面的这个决策
to genuinely impact employees
才能切实影响员工
like getting five days' work done in one day
那比如说五天的活让你一天干完啊
when there's no need for overtime
没有必要加班的时候呢
forcing you to work overtime
硬要你加班
based on groundless assumptions
按照毫无根据的这个推测
or off-the-cuff decisions
或者说拍脑门的决策
saying the project must go ahead
说这个项目必须得推进啊
ultimately leading to the project's failure
最终导致项目无疾而终
wasting resources and manpower
浪费人力物力
of course, that doesn't mean all bosses are incompetent
那当然也不是说所有老板都是蠢的啊
After all, the fact that a boss is in this position can speak volumes.
毕竟蠢老板坐到这个位置
It also reveals a lot about their capabilities.
也是能说明很多问题的
A survey by the Post-Wave Research Institute found that only 15% of employees believe their boss is all-powerful. So it's clear that most bosses are actually open to listening to their team. So don't underestimate your boss.
后浪研究所的一个调查发现说 只有15%的员工认为老板是唯我独尊的 所以可见 多数老板其实是听得进去大家的声音的 所以人家老板当傻子
Don't let some bosses' behavior on social media
不要因为有些老板在社交媒体上啊
skew your perception of them,
被这个曝光出来
just because they're labeled as brainless PUV non-stick pans or something.
说他是什么无脑PUV不粘锅
What about this super male and so on?
什么无脑这个超雄等等啊
Most bosses also need to hire people.
我们多数的老板也要用人
Most bosses are willing to listen to their employees' genuine voices and feelings.
多数老板都听得进去员工真心的声音和感受
Therefore, I believe that a boss's foolish decisions should be opposed.
那因此我认为老板的愚蠢决策是应该反对的啊
From a personal perspective,
那从个人层面来看啊
it's crucial.
很重要
It concerns you personally.
个人层面就关乎你
I exist as a working individual.
我作为牛马的一个生存
Opposing can effectively reduce necessary work pressure.
那反对是可以有效减少必要的工作压力的
Because once you comply with a foolish decision,
因为一旦你顺从了愚蠢的决策
You'll find that in the end, the one who suffers is still yourself.
你会发现其实最后遭殃的还是自己
I have a friend,
我有一个朋友啊
who is the head of software development for a certain company,
做这个软软软件的研发主管
but I don't do this myself,
真的因为我不做这个
he took on a project,
他接了一个项目
and followed the process,
就按照流程
expecting to complete it within two weeks,
这两周之内能干完
but his boss,
可是他们老板呢
insisted on using a new method that hadn't been tested for innovation,
非要用一个没有经过创新的新方法
which extended the two weeks to four.
就导致这两周就变成四周
So he has to work overtime for these extra two weeks But he's also the supervisor When he works overtime, he can't go home As a result, the project wasn't only delivered late We lost the client And almost lost his wife too
所以多出这两周他就得加班 但是他又是主管 他加班了就不能回家 导致就是项目不但没有按时完成交付 客户也没了 然后差点妻子也没了
The boss even added, after the fact
老板事后甚至补刀说
Why didn't you remind me back then?
你当时怎么不提醒我啊
So, in cases like this
所以说像这种类似
Sending these low-level minions to catch the Tang Monk and his disciples
让这种底层小妖去抓这个唐僧师徒啊
Such situations are really common in the workplace.
这种事在职场中真的是比比皆是啊
For example, what was supposed to be 10,000 yuan,
另外就是比如说本来是1万块钱
you're given a budget of 5,000.
预算就给你5000
Or even asked to organize a Spring Festival Gala with 5,000.
甚至让你花5000办个春晚
How is that even possible, right?
这种感觉怎么可能呢对吧
A task that ten people can complete in a week,
十个人一周干完的事
you're asked to finish alone in three days.
让你一个人三天完成
And then they set your KPIs unrealistically high,
所以这种东西包括给你KPI听的巨高
only to say at year-end that you didn't meet them,
最后间接可以说哎年底没完成
resulting in a halved bonus.
那分红减半
It could even affect your salary.
甚至可能影响你的工资收入
Do you agree or disagree with this?
这东西你反不反对
On the contrary, appropriately voicing your opposition
相反呢适当的提出反对意见
can not only prevent you from being blamed but also
不但能够避免这种我们说背锅还能啊
open up a reverse channel for promotion.
有一个反向的让你晋升的渠道啊
This channel is beneficial for individuals.
这个渠道呢是有利于个人的
Of course,
当然了
it’s especially suitable for young people who are eager to advance.
这适合我们说特别想进步的青年啊
So, after all that’s been said,
那所以说了这么多
are you all aware of this?
大家能意识到吗
It should truly encompass a diversity of voices to help our organization develop better through multidimensional thinking making rational decisions is what we should focus on As a psychologist making decisions especially group decisions
真正应该包含多元的声音 才能帮助我们能组织更好的发展 通过多维的思考 让组织做理性决策才是我们更应该做的 那我作为心理学者啊 做决策 尤其是这个群体决策
is a research area I am particularly passionate about
是我非常非常在意的研究领域
excessive conformity can lead to organizational inertia
那过度顺从会导致一个惯性的组织沉没
So, what does organizational inertia mean
那什么叫组织沉没
It's akin to group polarization
就近似于这个群体极化
or the spiral of silence scenario
或者说是沉默螺旋的情景
where you don't speak up
就是你不说
and neither does he
他也不说
or you take on this role
或者说你做这个角色
and he does too
他也做
he also complies fully
他也做全顺从
and in the end, this role becomes extremely extreme
最后这个角色非常非常极端
if foolish decisions are passed down layer by layer
如果说愚蠢的决策一层层地下达
and no one objects throughout the process
这其中没有任何人反对的话
The organization is likely to accelerate its decline.
组织很有可能加速衰亡
So, when facing a boss who plays a foolish role,
那所以呢面对老板的愚蠢角色
whether from a personal career perspective or from a business development perspective,
无论是从个人生涯角度还是从企业发展角度
I should believe that everyone should persist in
我都应该认为大家应该坚持
reasonably voicing their objections.
合理的提出自己的反对意见
Thank you all.
谢谢大家
Thank you both for your shares.
感谢两位老师的分享
Next, we'll move on to the question-and-answer session.
那接下来呢就进入到灵魂发问的环节
Each side will have one and a half minutes to ask questions to the other side,
双方各有一分半的时间向对方提问
and one and a half minutes to summarize their own questions.
并各有一分半的时间对自己的发问进行小结
The respondent's answer is not counted in the questioner's time. So, let's start by giving the floor to the opposition. One thing is, I feel that although you are the second-in-command, you are very modest, but you are also the boss of the company.
被提问方的回答是不计入发问时间的 那我们首先呢把时间交给反方 一个就是我觉得您本人虽然是二老板 您很自谦 但是也是公司的老板
So I'd like to ask you,
所以我想问问您
have your employees ever raised objections to you?
您的员工对您提过反对的意见
I'm actually not the kind of boss you might think I am.
我其实真的不是你们想象中那种老板的情况
If there were a second-in-command in your company,
你们公司但凡有一个二老板啊
you should know that it's a role that's often caught between a rock and a hard place.
你应该知道就是一个里外不是人的角色
The boss thinks you're not the boss.
老板觉得你不是老板
The employees wonder what gives you the right to represent us.
员工觉得你凭什么代表我们员工
So I'm basically in the middle.
所以我基本上在中间啊
It's really hard for me to navigate this situation.
我是很难做人的
I haven't really proposed any significant policies that the company wants.
我基本上没有提出过什么那种公司想要的方针
The policies from above,
上面的政策
I just pass them on as a messenger.
我当个传话筒得了
To get to the position of second-in-command,
能苟先苟当到二老板这个位子
it's not about opposing everything.
不是靠反对上来的
It's better to play it safe first.
是先苟上来好
So, actually, no army has presented a counterexample to you.
所以其实没有军队向您提的反例
Have you heard of these kinds of things on the internet?
那您听没听过像网上的这些就在网
For example, if you were the second-in-command.
比如说您是二把手
Do middle managers have similar issues with upper management?
中层有没有像高层的一些
I heard when I presented my argument earlier.
我听过我前面那个立论的时候
I often say,
我就经常说
I frequently disagree with my boss's opinions.
我说我经常反对老板的意见
Now I choose to comply.
我现在选择顺从
It's because I've already realized,
是因为我已经知道了
That opposing is futile.
反对没有用
He just wastes my energy a lot.
他只是非常浪费我的力气
And as the teacher mentioned earlier
然后包括像前面老师讲的
Opposition can effectively reduce unnecessary work stress I completely disagree with this I believe compliance will significantly reduce my work pressure. What are you talking about? Right, right, right I'll just go ahead and do it Because whenever I oppose my boss
反对会有效降低没有必要的工作压力 我觉得我完全不认同这个 我觉得顺从才会完全降低我的工作压力 你说什么啊 对对对 我就去做了就好了 因为我一反对老板
He says you're opposing this
他又说你反对这个
I need to tell you why he's great
我得告诉你他为什么好
You don't get it, do you?
你不懂吧
You're too young
你太年轻了
Let me explain that there's a reason for this
我来告诉你这个东西是有他的道理的
You'll understand in a couple of years
过两年你就知道了
I'll go have a chat with him
我去跟他进行这个对话
What for?
干什么
Right?
对不对
I just said okay
我就说嗯好的
I went and did it
我去做了
He waited three days before asking me anything.
他等三天再问我什么
The result was
结果
I said it’s in progress.
我说在做了
It’s in progress.
在做了
If he waits five days, he might change his mind.
等五天他自己可能换一个想法了
Then I wouldn’t have to do it.
我就不用做了
If we turn this into a
如果说把这事变成一个
budget issue, like we just mentioned,
就是我们刚才提到的一个预算问题
let’s say you have a budget of 5000,
假设给你5000预算
and you’re asked to do something worth 10,000 or even 100,000.
让你干1万或者10万的事情
He has a deadline for this.
他这个是有一个DDL的
There's nothing we can do about it.
那没办法
You're in the middle management, right?
您中层嘛
You might also have to lead a team.
您可能也是得带团队
What should we do then?
那怎么办呢
If it's an objective fact,
如果是客观事实的话
I suggest you bring this issue directly to your boss.
我这边建议把这个问题直接抛给老板
You could say,
你就说了
You've given me a budget of 5000,
你给我5000预算
But we need to accomplish work worth 10,000.
要干1万的活
You tell me what to do.
你说吧怎么办
I'll follow your lead.
我都听你的
But in a way, that's also a form of resistance.
那其实某种程度上也是一种反对
I don't personally see it as resistance.
我个人不认为这个是反对
Because I feel that what you're teaching me to do,
因为我觉得你教我做的事情
the fact that I'm pushing it forward is a form of compliance.
我在推进这个本身就是一种顺从
Resistance would be if I decided not to do it at all. But it's just outward compliance with inward resistance, isn't it? No, no, no, no. That could be a problem, hahaha. Well, I’d like to ask, as a middle manager and also a boss, have you ever made some foolish decisions?
反对是我觉得哦这个东西我不做了 但其实就是表面顺从内心反对啊 没有没有没有没有 这倒可以掐哈哈哈 那我想问问就是作为中层 也是老板 您偶尔做过一些愚蠢的决策吗
I definitely need to admit it openly.
那我肯定要大方承认哦
I think everyone has made foolish decisions at some point.
我觉得每一个人其实都做过愚蠢的决策的
It’s through these missteps that we
然后我们是在这些愚蠢的栽跟头的里面
learn and grow as individuals.
才学会自己的个人成长的
I don’t think anyone would stand up and say
我不认为有任何一个人站出来说
I’ve never made a foolish decision in my life
我这辈子都没有做过愚蠢的决策
before a decision is implemented.
在这个决策落地之前
Am I the divine farmer tasting a hundred herbs?
我神农尝百草吗
I won't take a bite.
我不吃一下
How would I know if it's poison or medicine?
我怎么知道它是毒药还是补药呢
I've taken it in.
我吃进去了
I'm starting to feel a reaction in my body.
我的我身体有反应了
There are objective facts and outcomes right in front of me.
他有客观的事实的结果摆在我面前了
Only then can it inform me.
他才能告诉我
Whether this was a smart or foolish decision.
我这到底是聪明的决策还是愚蠢的决策
Before there's an objective outcome for this thing.
这个东西没有一个客观的结果之前
I don't think anyone could predict it in advance.
我不认为大家是能提早预判到你
This is about being foolish or not.
这是愚蠢与否的
Let's wrap up this segment of soul-searching questions for now.
我们这个灵魂发问的环节暂告一个段落啊
Next, let's take a moment to summarize the questions we've asked.
那我们接下来发问小结的时间
Let's listen to his thoughts.
让我们来听一听他的心声
I think the opposition doesn't have to be confrontational.
那此时我认为给出的反对不一定要硬刚
You can offer some gentle counterpoints. The boss can actually be quite open to them. I have data to back this up, after all. But what if you encounter a situation where You feel the project has obvious issues. But your boss asks you to recommend You can say to your boss,
你可以给出一些温和的反对 其实老板是完全可以接受的 因为之前我也有数据支持啊 但是比如说你真的遇到了一个 你觉得有明显问题的项目 但是老板让你推荐 你就可以跟老板说
I think your idea is really great.
你说我觉得您这个idea真的很棒
First, you need to acknowledge your boss.
首先先得认可老板啊
And it has already been validated by other companies in the market.
而且已经被市场上其他公司哎验证过了
This indirectly tells you that it’s not innovative.
间接就告诉你这东西没创新
Then you need to wait for the right moment.
然后你要等待一个时机
Wait until your boss says, 'Well, what do you think?',
等老板说哎那你有什么想法啊
Come on, tell me how we should proceed.
啊你跟我说说应该怎么干
So at this point, smoothly present your solution.
所以此时呢丝滑的给出你的这个solution
Or your plan
或者说你的plan啊
The key isn't to confront your boss in public
重要的不是说在公共场合上怼老板
The real satisfaction of dissing your boss
DISS老板那种现实的爽感
It's about privately and calmly
通过私下跟老板去平和的
Expressing such disagreement in a gentle manner
去温和的表达这样的一个反对意见
This is crucial
是非常重要的
For us as individuals
那对我们刚才个人来讲
Indeed, voicing disagreement can help reduce work pressure
其实反对确实是可以减少工作压力啊
It's not about blindly conforming
不是说反对我去硬顺从啊
Excessive stress can harm your physical and mental health
压力过大不说你身心健康
As I mentioned earlier
刚才我说了
it can really cause significant problems
真的会出很大问题
let me explain why
我为什么这么说
I don’t need to do statistics
我不用做统计
I work as a psychological counselor
我做心理咨询
the cases of psychological counseling I receive each year
我每年接到的心理咨询个案
in companies
在企业里
workplace stress issues account for nearly half
职场的这种压力问题占到了将近一半
so I think people work to earn a living and support their families but they end up bringing health issues home This actually ends up being counterproductive for everyone. What's the point? Lastly, I want to emphasize a scientifically sound and reasonable opposition. Not only is there no risk, but it can even lead to a promotion.
所以呢我觉得出来上班图个挣钱养家糊口 那回家一身病 这个其实大家有点得不偿失 图什么 然后最后呢我想说就是科学合理的反对 不但没有风险 反而是能晋升的
Earlier, I mentioned that
刚才我提到了说
if you genuinely help the boss from the perspective of the company's growth,
如果你真的能从企业发展的角度去帮帮老板
go ahead,
去啊
think about it for him,
为他去想
the boss will actually value you more.
老板其实会更加看重你的
Of course, many employees have told me
当然很多员工跟我说
I just want to earn my own salary
我就想拿自己这份钱
I don’t really have any grand ambitions
我就没有什么远大抱负
It doesn’t matter
无所谓啊
After all, it’s just this way
因为毕竟是这个
We say that opposing promotion is a minority benefit
我们说靠反对晋升也是少数人的反对红利好
I’ll stop here
我说到这
Thank you very much, Teacher Yue, for sharing the workplace tips with us.
非常感谢愉悦老师给我们分享的职场技巧
But I’d like to add a friendly note
不过我特别想友情的补充一下
When we say to the boss, 'This idea of yours is really great'
当我们说老板你这个idea真的很棒的时候
Pay attention to your tone
注意语气
Otherwise, it can easily come off as sarcastic
不然很容易变成阴阳怪气
So, let's move on to the crucial questions from the affirmative side
那么接下来进入到我们正方的灵魂发问环节
Those who have worked should be able to tell the difference
上过班的朋友应该都能辨别出来
Is it a rare occurrence for a boss to be incompetent
老板愚蠢是一个很偶尔的事情
Or is it a frequent one
还是一个很经常的事情
When he comes up with over 40 ideas in a day
他一天提出40多个idea的时候
Do I have to sift through each one to figure out if he's being unreasonable
我要挨个去甄别他到底蠢不蠢
And which ones I should comply with
以及我哪个要顺从
And which ones I should oppose If I switch to a different class can I guarantee that I'll get a boss who isn't stupid? If your boss is intuitive and a normal person, of course out of 40, generally speaking, relying on this intuition
哪个要反对吗 如果说我换一个班上的话 我能保证遇到一个不蠢的老板吗 如果说你老板是直觉 也是正常的一个正常人的话啊 40个一一般来说凭借这种嗅觉
at least 80% should be fine
应该至少得有一个八成左右是问题不大的
it’s feasible
就是也有可行性的
but if you have 40
但是如果说40个
after the first round of screening
当你筛了第一遍之后
you'll find only four are left
你会发现就剩四个了
Then it proves that your boss might have issues with his initial business acumen.
那就证明你老板从最初的这种商业常识判断上
There might be a problem from the start.
可能就有问题
At this point, you shouldn't be thinking about compliance.
此时你应该想的不应该是顺从
You should be thinking about how to back out.
应该是想怎么撤嗯
I don't think that making significant business judgments is a sign of foolishness.
我不认为他商业重大判断那种东西是一种愚蠢
I believe the essence of foolishness is the lack of judgment.
我觉得愚蠢的本质就是没有判断能力
Once he can make business judgments,
他一旦能进行商业判断
it means he has his own considerations.
是他有他的考虑的
At this moment, what he considers foolishness,
这个时候就是他认为的愚蠢
is clashing with what I consider foolishness.
和我认为的愚蠢在对抗
Why should I assume that mine is definitely right?
那我凭什么认为我的一定是对的呢
I think there's actually an information gap.
其实我觉得这里面是有信息差
What the boss knows,
就老板了解的东西
might differ from what we, as employees, know.
跟我们作为员工了解的东西可能是有不一样的
I have a friend,
我有个朋友
who really does information flow promotion.
他真的做信息流推广啊
He conducts A/B testing.
他就做那a b test
He says he focuses on information flow advertising.
他就是说我做投信息流
If an information flow ad fails,
它其实如果投信息流如果要失败的话
the system will simply block it.
直接系统会卡掉的
But their boss is a time jump.
但是他们老板是空降来的
If he doesn’t understand the business, that’s a problem.
完全不懂业务这个事情就麻烦
He doesn’t know what he’s talking about. He gives you tasks. He’s the boss. And he’s guiding the people who do know. I can’t even stand it myself. If that were me, I’d be frustrated. I can barely tolerate it. It’s about not knowing the field. You should talk to someone who understands 123
就不懂的东西 他给你 他是领导 然后他指点你懂的人 我自己我都我都受不了了 就这种点放我身上 我都有点忍不了 就是你不懂这个领域 你去给懂的人说123
From this perspective
从这个角度讲
I think if you can make an initial judgment
我觉得你如果能初步的判断出来
that this is a foolish character
这个就是一个愚蠢角色的话
then it really should be as you just said
其实真的应该就是就刚才您说的
Don't wait until the volcano really erupts
别等火山真爆发了
You might not be able to run away by then
那会儿可能跑不动了
Considering whether the probability of the volcano erupting is high
因为那个那我是顺从火山概率爆发的几率高
or if the probability of it not erupting is higher
还是我反对他火山爆发的几率高
mainly based on the probability of the volcano erupting
主要从火山爆发的概率啊
It's essentially the decision-making at the top level.
其实就是顶层设计的那个决策
If it's someone at the middle level,
如果说是一个中层
I suppose your position should also be at the top level.
像说您的这个应该也是顶层设计啊
No, I'm just a workhorse.
没有我是牛马啊
We're talking about the top level here.
就是我们说的这个顶层
Generally speaking, it tends to be more strategic.
一般来讲它可能更多的是战略性的
If it's at the middle level,
那如果说是中层的
They might have to focus more on execution.
可能他更多会一个是他可能也要做执行
Another aspect is that we, as individuals, often focus on,
另外一个就是说我们个人更多多的是说
Indeed, there is a low-probability event.
确实是存在一个小概率的事件
But really, you know,
可是呢真的就是说
after I finished telling everyone that story, I realized, if a low-probability event really happens, the company might as well be gone. But if, as you said, the probability is not high, it doesn't mean I can't object.
在我刚才跟大家讲完这个故故事以后 就发现 如果真的是小概率事件发生的话 这个企业不不待也不待也罢 但如果说像您刚才说的概率并不高 但是不意味着我不能反对
I still want to truly express my voice
我还是要真正的表达出我的声音
Because expressing feelings is an emotion.
因为表达感受是一种情绪
We don't have to insist on opposition.
我们不要非要说反对
Opposition is more like a decision
反对更像是决策
Who makes the decision
决策是谁做的
Who makes the foolish decision
愚蠢决策是谁做的
It's not your employee, right
不是你员工做的对吧
You should express your feelings
你应该表达感受
After you hear about this role
就是当你听到了这个角色之后
I was initially shocked
我首先很震惊
Because I never expected my boss to make such a decision
因为我没有想到我老板能做出这样的决策
After being shocked
我感到了震惊之后呢
I tried to find ways to help my boss
我又想方设法帮助我老板
to take some kind of remedial action
去做一些什么样的补救
might be better
可能会更好
Based on my experience
根据我的经验
I think as an employee
我觉得作为一个员工
even if you’re a bit more experienced
作为一个稍微有经验
even if you just started
哪怕是你刚入职
if you want to appear more experienced to your boss
你想让老板看起来你比较有经验的情况下
you should first contain his decision
我应该你先收住他的这个决策
or you could first address his opposition
或者说你先把他的这种反对的
or his voice in the foolish role
或者说他的愚蠢角色的声音
Hold him back
你给他收住
and defuse his foolishness
然后化解了他的这个愚蠢
give him a little counter-question
给他一个小的反问
It seems like I'm a bit confused. Could you break it down for me? Explain it to me again This is where the role of middle management comes in, bridging the gap managing up shock your boss with PUA first then teach you how to do the job
就是诶我的感觉好像有一点点的不是很理解 您能给我再拆解出来 再给我讲一讲 这块可能就需要中层的这个承上启下的作用了 一种向上管理啊 PUA自己的老板先表达自己很震惊 然后教你怎么干活
Finally, tell him your ID, it's really great.
最后跟他说你的id呀可真棒呀啊
This is the method provided by Teacher Yu Yue.
这就是于越老师的给出的方法
Learn it and take notes right away.
学会了马上记笔记
Let's go straight into the next part.
那那我们就直接进入到
This crucial summary phase of the debate.
这个灵魂提问的小结阶段
Please let the affirmative side give their summary.
有请正方来进行小结
I think opposing it is the way to go.
我认为哈反对的话
A good outcome is the only real result.
好的结果才叫结果
A bad outcome is just a cost.
不好的结果叫代价
I oppose the idea of success.
我反对成功
What benefits can I get?
我能获得什么好处
If the opposition fails
反对不成功
What cost will I have to bear?
我要付出什么代价
The reason I've always been compliant
我一直坚持顺从的原因
is
就是
I think the most the boss would lose is just one employee
我觉得老板的代价最多就是失去我一个员工
But the cost was losing a job
但是我的代价是失去一份工作
This can have very different implications when it falls on an individual
这个东西落在个人头上是非常不一样的
If I push it to the extreme
我如果推到最极端
I'm asking Professor Yu here
我在这里问于老师
I think the boss's idea today is just too silly.
我今天觉得老板的这个想法太蠢了
I have to oppose him.
我一定要反对他
Would you dare to support me?
您敢支持我吗
If I risk losing this job,
如果说我面临着我要丢掉这份工作的风险
As a friend,
我作为朋友
I wouldn’t dare to support him either.
我是不敢去支持他就行了
I think you should just play it safe for now.
我就觉得你先苟着吧
Just go along with it for now.
你先顺从着吧
Then we can figure out a plan later. A career doesn’t necessarily have to be pursued through opposition. I often feel that opposition doesn't necessarily lead to ideal promotions. Opposition often makes your career more difficult. I don't even need to be unemployed.
之后再想办法 事业不一定是要通过反对去追 我往往觉得反对并不一定能换来理想的晋升 反对往往会让你在职场里过得更痛苦 我都不需要失业
He usually gives me a hard time.
他平时给我穿点小鞋
That's already tough enough for me.
我就够难受了
I don't want to embark on a long and arduous journey.
万里长征我不想走
I have a grain of sand in my shoe.
我鞋子里有一粒沙
I can't even get it out.
我都倒不出去
This is often what I experience in the nooks and crannies of life.
这个往往是我在生活当中的角角落落
What I can feel.
能感受到的
Don't bring up any grand ideals with me right now.
你这时候不用跟我提什么宏伟的远大理想
I can barely get through the petty struggles in front of me.
我眼前的苟且我都过不过去
Ah, I was actually quite moved just now.
啊刚才我其实也非常有感触
Because our side's Erda teacher mentioned that work is really something you can't afford to lose.
因为我们正方尔达老师说到工作真的是丢不起
This is a thorn in the side for many young people today.
这是现代很多年轻人心头的一块病
a heavy burden.
一块石头
Given this context,
那在这样的前提下
how can the debate proceed?
辩论怎么继续展开呢
Next, we'll move into the exciting and intense high-energy clash segment.
接下来就进入到紧张刺激的高能开杠环节啊
The two sides will take turns to speak.
双方交替发言
Each side has three minutes.
各有3分钟时间
We'll first invite the affirmative side to speak.
我们首先有请正方率先发言
In the past few years of work,
我上这几年班
my biggest takeaway is finally understanding the Chinese literature textbook,
我最大的感触就是终于理解了语文课本
what it means by 'people suffer in prosperity',
什么叫兴百姓苦
and 'people suffer in decline'.
亡百姓苦
When I complain about foolish decisions
我在抱怨决策愚蠢
When they can catch me off guard
能坑到我的时候
it seems that smart decisions also trip me up, I end up with nothing to gain either way. So, since I'm the one suffering anyway I don't think there's a need to oppose it I think the core issue is being taken advantage of
聪明的决策好像也坑到我 横竖都没有捞到什么好处 所以既然都是我受害的话 我就觉得这个东西是不需要反对的 嗯我觉得其实核心在于被坑
Regardless of the decision
甭管是什么决策
If it's about being taken advantage of
那如果是被坑的话
I personally think how to avoid pitfalls
我个人觉得如何避坑
Is a direction we need to continue living
是一个我们还要继续活下去
And even live better
甚至要活得更好的一个方向
So I wonder if Professor Zhang has any advice on avoiding pitfalls
所以不知道张老师有没有一些避坑的方向
I've always felt that having a choice is a luxury
我一直觉得有选择是一件很奢侈的事情
I don’t choose to oppose
我不选反对
Is it because I don’t want to oppose?
是因为我不想反对吗
I have a hundred voices of opposition in my heart
我心里有100个反对的声音
But what I show
但是我体现出来
My ultimate decision is to comply
我最终的决定是顺从
Is it because I have no choice?
是因为我没有什么选择
After losing this job
我失去了这份工作之后
Is there a better option waiting for me?
有什么眼前更好的选项在等着我吗
If there were a better option
但凡有一个更好的选项
I wouldn’t care whether to comply or oppose
我别管顺从还是反对
I'm getting rid of this
我抛弃这个
I just went straight there
我直接就去了
I think everyone is now compliant
我觉得大家现在顺从
because we often don't have better conditions in front of us
是因为我们眼前往往没有太好的条件
there are no better options
没有更好的选项
no higher platform to move forward
没有更高的平台往前走
when you don't have a better hand
在手里没有更好的牌的时候
people tend to seek benefits and avoid harm
人都是趋利避害的
what I can choose now is the best I have
我现在能选的就是我已经最好的了
I think Professor Zhang made a very important point earlier
我觉得刚才张老师说了一个非常重要的点
It's about how to avoid risks. But in my teaching career and my research career including when I was teaching at the university, I often share a principle with my students. Well, it's not exactly a principle, because it might be a hard-earned lesson,
在于这个如何去嗯避免风险 但其实在我的教学生涯和我做科研的生涯 包括我在大学教课的时候 我经常给大家讲一个道理 就是说其实也不是道理啊 因为这可能是血淋的教训
the issue of trial-and-error costs.
就是试错成本的问题
This is why we encourage young people to experiment and make mistakes.
就是为什么鼓励年轻人试错
Because, first of all, the cost of making mistakes in university is almost zero.
是因为首先在大学试错成本几乎为零
You can even switch majors.
你甚至可以转专业
Then you realize after switching majors,
然后你发现转完专业以后
the job you get,
你学的工作
has nothing to do with your major, right?
干的工作跟你专业没关系对吧
So, you need to understand,
所以其实你要知道
this is not a huge cost at all.
这完全不是一个多大的代价
Many people are overly concerned about the cost,
很多人很在意代价
but you find out in the workplace,
其实你发现到了职场以后
the cost is even greater.
代价更大
So, when it comes to young people,
所以放到年轻人身上
I personally encourage them to try and make mistakes.
我我个人是鼓励试错的
Especially in the first few years of transitioning from university to the workplace.
尤其是说从高校进入到职场的前几年
The cost of making mistakes isn't actually that high.
那些试错成本严格意义上也不大
Don't think that you have to stay at your first job forever.
因为你不要以为你就要在这第一家工作
Or that your second job will be your last.
第二家工作终老了
A lot of what you learn is part of your early foundation.
很多东西其实都是你的一个前期的积淀
You can rely on this to move forward in your career.
你可以靠着它往后去走
How can you enhance your resume?
那你的履历如何去提升
I think it's important to express your true thoughts at this point.
我觉得此时应该表达出你真实的想法
Regarding the idea of giving up and becoming numb.
就说躺平麻木这件事情
I suggest you work for 10 years and see how you feel.
我觉得你工作10年感受感受
I don't think it's necessary.
我觉得不用不用学的
So personally, I think if you're young now, especially the younger generation, if you want to voice your disagreement at this moment, it's important to express your concerns reasonably. even when you're older, talking to your own children, or boasting about it to others as a conversation starter,
所以个人觉得如果你现在尤其是年轻人 当下如果你想反对的话 合理地去表达出那个反对的点 哪怕等你老了以后 跟自己的孩子 跟别人吹牛的一个谈资
I think these are all very important.
我觉得这都是非常重要的
After all, you were young once too.
就是你曾经也年轻过
Haven't you heard Honglei say that if you're not passionate, you're not young?
红雷不是说过那个不气盛还叫年轻人吗
Right?
对吧
So I think this statement is really important.
所以我觉得这句话很重要
I feel like the teacher said a lot of encouraging words to me.
我感觉啊就是老师讲了很多鼓励我的话
A lot of support for your decision.
很多支持你的决定
Especially how young people should behave.
尤其年轻人要怎么样
I'm a young person too.
我也是年轻人
I graduated in 2020.
我20年毕业的
It hasn't been that long for me either.
我现在也没过几年啊
I have so many fears.
我害怕的事情太多了
I'm afraid of everything.
我都害怕
After this video goes live
这期视频上线之后
The big data recommended to my boss
大数据推给我的老板
if I say anything
我哪里发言
that's not right
发的不对
I won't have to go back to work
我就不用回去上班了
the teacher's words made me realize
老师的这些话让我感受到
I might have only become like this in recent years
我可能是近几年才变成这样的
if I had heard the teacher say these things when I was in school
我但凡上学的时候听到老师说这些话
I would have been greatly inspired
我一定会备受鼓舞
I want to be full of drive
我要成为有冲劲
With passion
有热血
Young people with a spark in their eyes
眼里有光的年轻人
But as I was listening just now
但我刚才听的时候
I found myself thinking
我会想说
Whether the teacher's correct words
老师的这样的正确的话
Are applicable in any era
是否是在任何时代都适用的
It's right to say this this year
今年讲这句话是对的
But will it still hold true next year When I heard those words just now I suddenly had a flashback to the Winter Solstice I spent back home My uncle from the sixties and seventies would often tell me things like this
明年讲这句话还有还有用吗 我刚才听这句话的时候 我就是有一种我突然想起了我回去过冬至啊 我六七十年代的那个叔叔 他就会经常跟我讲这种话
you know, why is it so hard for you guys now
就是哎为什么你们现在这么难呢
I think it's still okay
我觉得还好的吗
why do you all seem to say that your income is less than last year
为什么你们今年好像都说收入比去年减少了
why are there so many issues
为什么为什么有这么多
why do I get the feeling that you've benefited from the times
为什么给我一种你们吃到了时代的红利
you haven't been caught in the rain
没淋过雨
and you're asking others why they have umbrellas
到处问别人为什么撑伞
but I feel like the rain here is already pouring heavily
但这种感觉我这里雨已经下得那巨大
It was as big as the day we stole the electric scooter with Naoki
跟直树偷电瓶车那天那么大
It's like when Yiping asked her dad for money
跟依萍找她爸借钱
It was raining so heavily that day
那天那么大雨
You ask me why I have an umbrella
你问我为什么撑伞
And then you tell me to object
然后这时候你叫我反对
To resist
叫我反抗
What am I supposed to resist
我反抗什么
Am I supposed to resist the rain from falling
我反抗让雨别下了
I don't think that makes any sense
我觉得没有这个道理
Given the heavy rain
在下大雨的情况下
With no place to hide
我们无处可躲的情况下
Not knowing what to object to
我也不知道能反对什么的情况下
Holding an umbrella myself is the best choice I can make
我自己撑把伞是我能做的最好的选择
And there was another point the teacher mentioned earlier
然后还有一句老师刚才讲的时候
Because I thought about my college days
因为我想到了我的大学的时光
So it made me think of a saying
所以我觉得让我想到了一句话
That brave people get to enjoy the world first
叫做勇敢的人先享受世界嘛
I don’t think that way anymore
我现在不这样想了
Now I believe brave people first accept the world After accepting the truth of the world I'm still striving to live my life. This is what I currently consider to be bravery. Teacher Zhang mentioned the rainy day just now. I was particularly touched by it. At that moment, the song that came to my mind was Incessant Rain.
我现在觉得勇敢的人先接受世界 接受了这个世界的真相之后 我依然在努力的生活 这是我目前认为的勇敢 张老师刚才说的那个下雨的 我特别有感触 当时我的脑脑回路就有一首歌叫雨一直下
The next line goes, 'The atmosphere isn't quite right'.
然后下边一句话叫气氛不算融洽
The atmosphere wasn't quite right.
那气氛不算融洽
It's actually talking about the corporate culture that a company provides to its employees.
讲的其实就是企业文化的一个给到大家的
When a company doesn't allow it,
就是当一个企业不允许
there's no atmosphere to speak of.
你是没有气氛可言的
I wasn't happy in there.
我在里边是不快乐的
If I'm not happy,
那我不快乐的话
then I might just be surviving.
那我可能就是苟活着
That's why young people say, um,
所以为什么说年轻人说呃
I quickly learned to be numb.
我很快就学会了麻木
Learned to lie flat.
学会了躺平
But I personally think we really shouldn't in this era.
但我个人觉得真不应该在这个年代
Even if the times are tough,
哪怕是接的那个说时代不好
Because I strongly agree with this statement.
因为我特别认同这句话
I never say it's your fault.
就是我从来不会说这是你们的错
At the same age
同样的年龄
you guys are way more capable than I was back then
你们比我当年能力要牛逼很多很多很多
I genuinely feel this way
我真心是这么觉得的
because every time I see my graduating students
因为我看到每一届我毕业的学生
I think, how can they be so strong
我都觉得怎么那么强
they are just incredibly impressive
就是一个太厉害了
so I don’t think it’s your fault if you can’t find a job
所以我觉得找不到工作不是你们的错
it’s just that there are fewer opportunities and your capabilities have become even stronger this wall is definitely a result of continuous improvement That's why we have a round of applause for Teacher Yu Yue's wonderful speech.
只是确实是机会少了 而你们的能力又变强了 这个墙一定是迭代出来的强 所以才会有卷感谢于越老师的精彩发言啊
As the competition progresses further,
因为比赛越来越深入
we've indeed touched on many topics concerning young people.
确实聊到了很多关于年轻人的话题
Should we choose to accept reality,
究竟应该选择接受现实
become numb or lie down?
麻木或者躺平
Or should we maintain our sharpness,
还是保有锐气
and our vigor?
保有盛气
Now, let's hand over to the affirmative side,
那接下来交给正房
for Teacher Er Da to summarize the debate.
我们尔达老师进行开杠小结环节
During the exchange with Teacher Yu,
跟于老师交流的这个环节当中
I came up with a word
我想到了一个词
it's 'dislike of stupidity'
就是厌蠢
who is it that we keep admiring all day long?
我们一天到晚到底是谁在艳唇
I just thought about it
我刚心想了一下
I think it's often us, the ones who seem to have read a bit
我觉得往往是我们这些好像读了点书的
with decent education
学历还不错的
constantly finding this stupid
天天看这个觉得蠢
that stupid
那个觉得蠢
but can't take off this long robe
但是脱不下这个长衫
we seem to do nothing but dislike stupidity
我们好像除了厌这个蠢
making myself angry
让自己生气
besides torturing myself both mentally and physically
折磨得自己身心俱疲之外
there’s not much else I can do
也没有什么别的办法
so my current thought is
所以我现在的想法是
this world isn’t just made up of us
这个世界不单单是由我们组成的
foolishness and contempt are often mutual
愚蠢和鄙视这个东西很多时候是相互的
from something as big as independent directors funding their own films
大到有一些独立导演自己贴钱拍电影的时候
some people think they’re foolish
有些人觉得他蠢
to something as small as me not getting married at 29 others also think I’m pretty foolish So, who exactly has the right to make such a foolish definition? I think the boss's foolishness or wisdom is irrelevant. I don't really care about that decision.
小到我29岁不结婚 别人也觉得很我很蠢 所以到底是谁有这个愚蠢的定义的权利 我认为老板的愚不愚蠢的 这个决定是我不在意的事情
What I should focus on is
我应该更在意的是
which of my own decisions are wise,
我自己心里哪一些决定是明智的
and which are foolish.
哪一些决定是愚蠢的
As for him, he's just a part of my job.
至于他只是我的一份工作
I do what's expected of me.
我做好我份内的事情
I'm finding my value elsewhere
我在其他的地方找我的价值
I think what Mr. Zhang said is very important.
我觉得张老师说的一点非常重要
It's about following the new, right?
就是随从新对吧
We need to listen to our inner voice.
要问我们内心的声音
It can also be restated as 'follow your heart', right?
可以重新就是follow your heart对吧
It can also be called following, right?
也可以叫做从嘛
The heart below might waver.
下边一个心就怂
But I don't encourage everyone to waver when they're young.
但是呢我不鼓励大家年轻的时候就怂
Because I'm not that kind of person myself.
因为我本身不是这样一个人
But I wouldn't immediately jump to conclusions.
但是呢我不会有想法立刻跳脚
I would find support.
我会找到支持
Find people who share my thoughts.
就找到跟我有想法的人
Let's all go online and give suggestions.
一起去网上去提建议啊
I think these are all practical and solid tips.
这些我觉得都是一些就是实打实打实
These are some directional techniques that everyone can use.
大家能用到的一些方向性的技巧啊
Another point I feel is important for young people is:
另外呢我会觉得说年轻人还有一个点
Or, what’s another point about new entrants to the workplace? They tend to procrastinate. They often wait around. They keep waiting, thinking someone else will do it. But you'll find that this is referred to as in our social psychology as diffusion of responsibility. It's like a tug-of-war You always think he's putting in effort
或者说现在职场新人还有一个点是什么呢 是老喜欢拖 老喜欢等 就我等等他我等等他 可是你会发现这部在我们社会心理学里面叫 责任分散 就是就跟拔河子似的 你老觉得他使劲了
He thinks you're putting in effort
他要觉得你使劲
In the end, you both lose
最后你们就输了
But in reality, no one is really trying
但是其实没人使劲
In the end, you'll find the boss saying, 'Why didn't you raise any concerns?'
最后你会发现说老板说你们怎么没提意见
He says, 'I thought you would bring it up'
他说哎我以为你会提
I thought you would bring it up
我以为你会提
It's a tough situation
妈拳头硬了
That's the feeling
就是那种感觉
It's just that no one ever brings it up.
就是压根没人提啊
So, we often say that when people have ideas,
所以呢我们经常会说大家有想法的时候
they should at least express them.
至少先表达出来
I've never said I'm against the idea.
我说想法我从来没说反对
Actually, this debate topic is a bit off track.
其实本身这个辩题有点跑题
I prefer to turn opposition into ideas or feelings.
就是我更倾倾向于把反对变成想法或者感受
I think this is something everyone should bear in mind.
我觉得这是大家应该铭记在心的
You really need to express your feelings.
就是你真要把你的感受表达出来
It's just a matter of different positions.
就就是立场不同啊
But you need to stick to your position.
就是但是你要坚持住立场
Why is that?
为什么呢
Because only the brain can be foolish.
因为愚蠢的只是脑袋
Just make sure your butt isn’t foolish.
你的屁股别愚蠢就行了
Do you get what I mean?
懂我意思吗
I mean, stand your ground.
就是你站在你的立场上
Speak up for your own position.
你要为自己的立场说话
Don’t just stand there like that.
你别站在自你站在这好像
But your mind isn’t in it.
但是你心思不在这
So your butt can stay smart. I’m really enjoying sitting on this stage. I'm the audience member closest to both debaters We are about to enter the final free summary phase
所以屁股可以不愚蠢啊 我坐在台上非常的享受 我是离双方辩手最近的观众 我们马上就要进入到最后的随便总结阶段
Let’s have a summary of the entire debate competition
给我们全场辩论比赛进行一个总结
Each side has 4 minutes to speak
双方各有4分钟的发言时间
Next, we invite Teacher Yu Yue from the opposition to give a summary
接下来我们就有请反方于悦老师来做一个总结
Actually, we feel that we have been too good at conforming since childhood
我其实我们觉得我们从小就太擅长从众了
Because conformity itself is
因为从众这个事情本身就是
the influence of collectivism in our culture
既有我们文化的这种集体主义的影响
And the generational transmission within our families
也有我们说原生家庭的一个呃代际传递的作用
However, I believe that behind conformity, there’s definitely an aspect of psychology
可是呢我觉得从众背后一定是学过心理学的
We all know that it's underpinned by the pressure of a collective.
都知道它背后是一个集体压力的约束
But as social beings,
但我们作为社会人
we are actually deeply afraid of being isolated.
其实骨子里其实是很担心被孤立的啊
Even if we take a huge step back,
那退1万步讲
you’re not afraid of being isolated,
你不怕被孤立
many people’s inner voice says,
很多人内心的OS就是说
I don’t really care about the company’s true direction anyway,
反正我也不太在意企业真正的走向
I just need to get my paycheck,
我就拿我那一份工资就可以
it doesn’t affect my regular salary,
不影响我正常发工资
I don’t want to be the one sticking my neck out.
我不要做那个出头鸟
I think this can all be understood.
我觉得这个都可以理解
But if this goes on for too long,
但是长此以往
you might end up convincing yourself
你甚至最后会说服自己
that you actually like it this way.
我好像就是喜欢这样
It's as if you've achieved self-consistency. This self-consistency is actually to avoid cognitive dissonance. In essence, it's a form of self-PUA. Personally, I believe that when considering all the practical factors, I'm here to wrap up the debate for everyone.
就相当于说你达到了自洽 这个自洽其实是为了避免认知失调导致的自洽 本质上这是一种自我PUA 个人觉得其实在综合考虑现实因素的情况下 我给大家就是结辩嘛
proposed some methodologies
就提出了一些这个方法论上的这个呃
Let's interpret the first point we mentioned earlier.
解读一个就是我们刚才提到的
When you encounter a project that doesn't work out.
碰到不行的项目
First, learn how to communicate with your boss.
先跟老板怎么去说话术
When you review the recording later.
到时候回头大家看那个重放的时候
You can take notes for yourself.
自己记下来就可以
If you have any issues, don't voice them on the spot.
然后就是有意见不要在现场说
Don't criticize in front of everyone.
不要现场DISS
Handle it more peacefully in private.
私下peace一点解决
Another important point is to avoid relying on past experience blindly.
然后另另外就是千万不要搞经验主义那套
Don't say to your boss, 'I used to do this.'
说老板我原来干这个的
I have a lot of experience.
我特有经验
You can put your methods here.
您那一套你放在这
The boss really doesn't like to hear that.
老板是真的不爱听的
Especially don't compare me to your previous boss.
尤其是别比说我原来老板
And I won't even mention what comes after that.
而你啊这后头的话我都不说了
These are the conventional sentence patterns we use.
就是这些套用的惯例这个句型啊
We shouldn't overuse them too much.
咱们就不要太太太多太多去用
And always be logical and evidence-based.
然后一定是有理有据的啊
From the boss's perspective.
在老板的视角
Consider things from the company's perspective.
从公司的视角去考虑
Also, I believe in leading by example.
另外呢就是我个人觉得就做人先做己
This saying.
这句话
I recommend starting with small things to show your capabilities.
我个人建议大家就是先通过一些小的地方
Little details.
小的方面
First, prove yourself to your boss.
先在老板面前证明一下自己
Show your boss that you have actually accomplished something.
就证明让老板觉得唉
That you've at least achieved something.
其实你至少还做过
Even a small success. Rather than just voicing objections. Just being negative all the time. I think this is not advisable. Instead, we should not oppose just for the sake of opposing. We should reduce the likelihood of harm to our mental and physical well-being caused by foolish actions. Because, after all, life is tough.
有有一个小成果 而不是你只说反对意见 只是唱反调 这我觉得是不提倡的 然后我们觉得不应该为了反对而反对 而是去降低一些由于愚蠢角色下场 导致我们个人身心受损的这样的一种可能性
I have dealt with a lot of cases.
因为真的毕竟生活不易
They are truly due to immense life pressures.
我接触了大量的个案
There are mortgage payments to be made.
真的都是因为生活压力太大了
Car loans, and so on.
要还房贷
And there are children to raise.
还车贷等等
Then he found that he had to do this job.
还要养孩子
But he complied.
可是是顺从了
But my body really can't take it anymore.
可是我的身体真的吃不消
There will come a day when I can't keep up.
真有一天我干不动了
What should we do?
怎么办
Because I've done a lot of research.
因为我做了很多研究
Psychological research.
心理学研究
Research on family relationships.
因为做家庭关系
Mainly focusing on intimate relationships.
亲密关系比较多
And workplace relationships.
然后职场关系
I also handle interpersonal relationships
人际关系我也做
The essence of interpersonal relationships lies in
其实本质人际关系的核心在于什么
communication
就是沟通
When you find communication isn't going well
你发现沟通不顺
you might be less inclined to communicate
你就不想沟通了
This could be because you feel the person doesn't respond
这可能是因为你觉得这个人不反馈
They keep sending me messages
就是他老给我发信息
Like, they send ten messages at a time
你看老发十条信息
You don't reply
你不回
Or you reply with just one
或者你回一条
Go take a shower or something like that.
你去洗澡啊什么之类的
These things don’t have any substantial content.
你这些东西没有没有任何实质性的内容
So people don’t want to communicate.
所以大家就不想沟通了
But I genuinely recommend that everyone
可是我真心建议大家
Especially in companies,
尤其是在企业里面
It’s still important to set up something like this within your own company,
在自己的公司里面还是应该建立那么一个
Of course, I know you all have your own small groups already,
至少我当然知道你们自己有很多小群了啊
There will definitely be internal communication groups,
就是一定会有那种内部沟通群
Even if these groups can’t really influence the final decisions, At least they can help us communicate internally. There's a release and relief of emotions I think this is also very important for the present
这个沟通群哪怕是真正无法影响最终角色 但是至少能让我们自己内部 有一个情绪的释放和缓解 我觉得这个在对于当下来讲也是非常重要
And it's practical
且这个务实的啊
Personally, I feel that
我个人觉得就是嗯
We shouldn't let a culture of power become the core of the company
不要让权力文化成为公司的核心啊
Or the core of the business
或者说企业的核心
Because power, at its essence, is a significant concession
因为权力本质就是我们对这的一个高的让步
A compromise
妥协
Such as compliance and so on
什么顺从等等
But you need to understand that corporate culture, as mentioned earlier, is crucial
但是你要知道企业文化刚才说了对吧
Stealing electric scooters in the heavy rain
下着大雨偷电瓶车
This kind of tense atmosphere under his protection
这种羽翼之下气氛不融洽的这种状态
Actually, over time
其实让你久而久之
It seems like there’s no immediate impact on you
你看起来好像没有什么短期影响
You’re not in pain
你不疼
But when the real pain hits
可是真的让你疼的时候
You realize it’s in the late stage
你发现是一个晚期
It’s that feeling when you realize the problem is huge
就是那种感觉你已经发现问题很大
And you find out that the real late stage isn’t painful at all
而且你发现真正的晚期根本也不疼
So from this perspective
所以从这个角度来讲
We shouldn’t let it become a stable practice.
我们不应该让它成为一种稳定的
Or one that is encouraged,
或者说一种被鼓励
the advocated culture and ideology
被提倡的文化和意识形态
This inevitably leads to social rigidity and decay.
所以呢就说不避免导致社会僵化腐朽啊
I think the core issue is about
我我觉得核心的东西在于什么
the loss caused by foolish work practices,
在于如果工作愚蠢带来的这个损失
resulting in more workload,
是为什么更多工作量啊
affecting future performance evaluations.
为我未来的这个绩效啊
Bearing with it can be understood,
忍一忍可以理解
but being forced to drink is another story. Being forced to tell dirty jokes These and other forms of harassment Even some legal issues For instance, some pharmaceutical companies to commit insurance fraud
但是你说被迫喝酒 被迫开黄段子 这些开等等一些骚扰等等 甚至有一些法律法律问题 比如说某些药企为了骗保
From top to bottom
从上往下
Actually, you know the right thing to do
其实你是知道道理的
A foolish character
愚蠢的角色
This is not just foolish
这不不但是愚蠢
It’s downright fatal
简直就是致命的角色
You end up complying
你跟着顺从了
I think it should be fine
你觉得应该没问题
The boss is holding things down for now
老板先顶着呢
But in the end, you realize everyone is actually reporting together
可是最后你发现其实大家一起报啊
Finally, let's talk about this word
最后再说顺着这个字
This word is used very cleverly
顺着这个字用的很巧妙
As you can see, gentle like a lamb
就是你看温顺如绵羊
But it can also be an ox or a horse, right?
但也可以是牛马对吧
So we say that today the boss's foolish role can be submissive
所以我们说今天老板的愚蠢角色被顺从也可以
But it can also be opposed
但是被反对也可以
But what it absolutely cannot be is
但是唯独不可以的是
When it is pointed out as foolish
当其被指出为愚蠢时
compliance should still be promoted as the right choice
顺从仍要被当作正确的选项来倡导
So employees should comply with their bosses
所以说职员就应该顺从老板呀
Lower-power individuals should comply with higher-power individuals, these social norms
低权力者就应该顺从高权力者这些社会规训
I genuinely believe that what should be is not what is
我真心认为不应该成为应当
Absolutely brilliant
非常精彩
Finally, we invite the affirmative side, Teacher Erdal, to give a casual summary
最后我们有请正方尔达老师做随便总结
I think when I chose the position of the affirmative side
我觉得我当时选这个正方的立场呢
Actually, he doesn't share my stance. He is my predicament A lot of what I said today might sound like I'm trying to get away with something I am taking advantage of everyone's work-related frustration to get an unfair benefit I guess I'm a bit of a
其实他不是我的立场 他是我的困境 我今天讲的很多话呃 听起来是有耍赖的嫌疑的 我是有利用大家的上班愤怒的这个情绪的 是占便宜的 我觉得我这人有一点怎么说啊
A bit of cynicism, perhaps.
有点犬儒主义吧
as I mentioned earlier
我感觉像我前面说的
when you have no cards in your hand
手里没牌的时候
staying at the table is the best chance to hang on
你先留在牌桌上就是最大的机会苟住
we will eventually draw good cards
我们会摸到好牌的
Our company offers a monthly leave policy.
我们公司是有月进假的
Female employees can take one day off each month.
女员工每个月可以放一天假
We have a male boss.
我们是男老板
There’s no way she proposed this role.
这角色不可能是她提的
It couldn’t have been the young Karami either.
也不可能是当时还是小卡拉米的
I only suggested it after I became the second-in-command.
我踢的是我成为了二老板之后才可以提的
I feel we have always been
我觉得我们一直是
dancing on a very limited stage.
在一个非常有限的舞台上面跳舞
What we constantly strive for is a very limited form of fairness.
我们不断争取的是很有限的公平
Moving up the ladder.
往上走
There's a chance for us to write our own version of fairness
才有自己书写公平的可能
So when I looked at this question
所以我看这个题的时候
I didn't think about opposing foolishness
我想的不是反对愚蠢
I thought about our participation in decision-making
我想的是我们要参与决策
I've never conformed to my boss's decisions
我顺从的从来不是老板的决策
I conform to the direction my heart desires I just move forward straight ahead I'll see where I end up I might not be able to leave behind any grand thoroughfares But the path I've walked
我顺从的是我自己内心要去的方向 我就径直往前走 我走到哪里算哪里 我可能没有办法留下什么伟大的那种康庄大道 但是我走过的路
This way, those who come after me will have an easier path.
自然会让我后面的人更好走一些
My stance is to adopt a confrontational attitude
我的态度就是用对抗的姿态
There will always be challenges to confront.
就会有对抗不完的事情
You'll end up stuck in the same spot.
你就会把自己困在原地
When we walk through a thorny path,
我们穿过一条荆棘路的时候
if you try to cut every thorn in front of you,
如果你要斩断你眼前每一根刺的话
you won't be able to move forward.
你就前进不了了
I think of a saying: life is short, only 30,000 days.
我想到有一句话叫人生短短3万天
Our time,
我们的时间
our energy is very limited.
我们的精力是非常有限的
Don't waste your energy fighting against foolishness
不要把力气花到对抗愚蠢上
We should fight against injustice
我们应该对抗不公
Fight against discrimination
对抗歧视
Spend your energy on reading books that are more valuable
把力气花到更有价值的地方去看书
Use your energy to learn a skill
要力气的学习一项技能
Use your energy to save money for travel
要力气的我攒钱去旅游
Seeing a bigger world requires a lot of energy
看更大的世界需要很多很多的力气
When I don't have energy
我没有力气的时候
I can't even express the most ordinary care to my family and friends
我连对家人朋友表达最平常最日常的关心
I can't do it at all
我都做不到
So, when it comes to dealing with foolishness
所以对待愚蠢这个态度上
My stance is to ignore it. I'm a very humble person what I can do is to cultivate my own character achieve a little success attain a bit of happiness every era produces people like me but I believe a better world
我的态度就是无视 我是一个很小我的人 我能做到就是独善其身 取得一点小小的成就 获得一点小小的幸福 每个时代都会产生我这样的人 但是我觉得一个更美好的世界
does indeed require more people to be like Teacher Yu
确实需要更多的人成为于老师这样的人
Let me share a small insight with all of you.
我跟大家分享一个小的感悟吧
I feel like I used to drift through life.
我觉得我以前活的也挺漂浮的
Ever since I accidentally drove my car into a field two years ago,
自从两年前我不小心把车开到田里之后
because everyone made fun of me,
因为大家嘲笑我
I decided to get a racing license.
我去考了个赛车证呃
My coach taught me a few moves.
我的教练教了我几招
During countless anxious nights,
在无数个焦虑的深夜里面
these few words,
这几句话呃
often pulled me out of the fire.
往往拯救我于水火之中
The first one is, 'It won't kill you.'
第一句不会死的
The second one
第二句
Anything can happen.
什么情况都有可能发生
Don't worry about others.
你不要管别人
Focus on
管
finding your own opportunities.
你自己找机会
The third point is once you get on the track,
第三句是你开到赛道上之后呢
it's completely different from sitting in a classroom and operating a simulator.
就跟坐在教室里开模拟器是完全不一样了
Especially when you put on this helmet,
尤其是戴上这个头盔之后
your field of vision will narrow.
你的视野会变窄
There's no way around it.
这是没办法的
And you need to have him step up after that. You can be flexible in your adjustments. What should you pay attention to? What should you ignore? Where your eyes look is your field of view. That’s where your vision lies. I really liked this quote at the time. Because I misunderstood it.
而且是你需要他上去之后 你可以灵活调整 你该注意什么 该无视什么 你眼睛看哪里 哪里就是视野 我当时特别喜欢这句话 因为我听错了
I was captivated by the idea that where your eyes look,
我倾城的是你眼睛看哪里
that’s where your career is headed.
哪里就是你的事业
Alright.
好
So, let's welcome Professor Jiang to share with us online.
那么下面就有请蒋老师在线上跟我们分享一下
Regarding the entire debate competition,
他关于整场辩论比赛
feel free to express all your thoughts.
所有的想法
You can speak your mind freely.
您都可以畅所欲言
I thought the previous debate was incredibly impressive.
刚才那场辩论呢我觉得打的非常惊艳
The two professors didn’t seem like they were debating for the first time at all.
两位老师完全不像第一次打辩论
They delivered a truly outstanding debate.
是贡献出了一场非常精彩的辩论
Or rather, a profound discussion.
或者说是探讨啊
There were many highlights.
看点很多
So, as I mentioned at the beginning, this debate should have three fronts.
那么这场我在最开始说的战场应该是有三个
Looking at this from the employees' perspective
就是从员工角度去看这个事
First, from the organizational management angle
第一个啊组织管理的角度去看
Second
第二个
And also from the societal or public angle
还有就是从全社会或者公共性的角度去看
This is the third one
这是第三个
Now, Teacher Zhang from the affirmative side focuses on the first battlefield
那么正方张老师主打的是第一个战场
Here
这里呢
Teacher Zhang first sheds his identity as the second boss
张老师首先把自己二老板这个身份给拆掉了
Because the boss identity
因为因为老板这个身份
isn't very appealing in this topic
在这个题里面不是很讨喜
He said the second boss is in a tough spot, caught between two fires.
他说二老板里外不是人
In the company, it’s still best to follow the top boss. This helps to reduce the tension between him and the employees. And he says he stands on your side. Ladies and gentlemen, the opposing side, Don’t talk without feeling the pain.
在公司还是得顺从大老板 这个就消解了自己和员工之间的对立性 那么而且他是说我是和你们站在一边的啊 大家对方辩友 你不要站着说话不腰疼
Because the cost of opposing the boss is too high.
因为反对老板的代价太高了
Employees don’t need to overthink things for the company.
员工没有必要为员为公司想太多啊
There’s no such thing as right or wrong.
哪有什么是非对错
We workers just do what the boss says.
我们打工人老板说说啥
You got it.
你对对对
Just carry on and get it done.
接着做就完事了
This way, at least you won't get fired.
这样这样至少你不会被辞退
This is a classic slimming-down strategy in debates.
这是一种辩论中很经典的瘦身打法
I lowered my position
就是我把我的位置降低
I'm just an ordinary person.
我就是个普通人
Don't push me to be noble.
你们别逼我高尚
I'll act based on my own interests.
我就从我自己的利益出发
This approach works if the opponent is quite paternalistic.
这种打法如果对方是就是爹味儿比较重
Acting all high and mighty, preaching down to others.
高高在上说教
Then I'll show you how to handle things.
然后教你做事
If the other party adopts this attitude, it can be surprisingly effective.
那么如果对方这个姿态会有奇效
Because everyone tends to empathize with an individual's situation.
因为大家都会带入和共情个体处境
However, on the one hand, Teacher Yu is quite cunning and sly.
但是呢一方面这个于老师是很阴险狡猾的
He is gentle and refined.
他温文尔雅
A set of soft and yielding techniques.
一套化骨绵掌
He doesn’t speak from a position of superiority.
他也没有站在高处说话
And he isn’t aggressive at all.
然后呢他也没有什么攻击性
What he says is all very reasonable.
他这他说的都是啊
I fully understand the challenges young people face.
我很理解年轻人处境
I speak for you as well.
我也为你们说话
I understand your stance.
我理解你们的态度
This makes Teacher Zhang's slimming strategy feel like hitting a pillow. On the other hand, there's an issue with slimming. If you keep slimming down, you might end up overdoing it. It becomes difficult to build value. Because I am no one to anyone. No one cares. I don’t care about the company or society.
这个就让张老师的瘦身打法有点打在棉花上了 另一方面就是瘦身存在一个问题 你如果瘦瘦瘦瘦瘦 一直瘦瘦过头了 你就很难建构出价值 因为我谁也不是我 谁也不管 我不管公司或者不管社会
So, you can only concede the second and third fronts to the other side.
那么你第二个战场和第三个战场
You can only give those to the other side.
你只能让给对方了
If you lose too much weight,
如果你瘦过头了
We can see a similar situation in this debate.
那这场辩论中也能看到类似的情况
From the perspective of Teacher Zhang as an employee,
就是张老师在员工的角度
From an individual's perspective,
个体的角度角度
He constructed this meaning of compliance.
他构构建了这个顺从的意义
I think his final point was really great.
他最后那个说法我觉得是很棒的
I'd like to expand on what he said.
我再延伸一下他说的话
Actually, this debate topic
就是其实呢这道辩题
From a certain perspective, we can draw an analogy to a human life.
某种角度上我们可以类比为人的一生
Life, in a sense, can be seen as an unavoidable journey.
人生在某种程度上可以当做一种没法没法回避
And it’s also hard to resist.
然后也很难抵抗
Often, it’s also an unreasonable trip.
然后很多时候也并不合理的一趟旅程
The relationship between you and your boss might be similar.
跟你和你老板之间的关系
It’s a kind of analogy.
也许是可以类似的
In such a situation,
就类比的
in your life,
那么在这样的一个情况下
you might endlessly oppose and complain about this fate.
你在你在你的生活中
Or the arrangement of the environment
或者说环境的安排呢
Or to some extent accept it
还是说在一定程度上接受
And then focus on oneself
然后专注于自身呢
Professor Zhang advocates this value
那么张老师打的就是这个价值
Which is about broadening your perspective
就是看到的就是你的视野
I think this is a great value proposition from an individual standpoint
我觉得这是一个非常棒的在个体角度上的价呃
Value advocacy The first battle ended in a draw Or I think Professor Zhang had a slight edge But the initiative in the next two battles was in Professor Yu's hands Earlier, Teacher Yu discussed corporate management innovation
价值倡导 那么第一个战场打了个旗鼓相当 或者说张老师我觉得还略胜一筹 但是后两个战场主动权就掌握在了于老师这边 刚才于老师从公司管理 从创新
and the questioning spirit that young people should have
从年轻该有的这种质疑精神呀
or their initiative
或者主观能动性啊
to construct opposing values on multiple levels
多层次的建构了反对的价值
and his expression was clear and fluent
而且他的表达清晰流畅
which clearly showed he came well-prepared
一看就是有备而来
and Teacher Yu also managed to do both
而且呢于老师还做到了一边
express his own views
他说自己的观点
while also sharing some knowledge points from psychology
一边还讲了一些心理学中的知识点
No wonder you're a knowledge zone UPloader
不愧是知识区up主
You really gave the audience a sense of gain.
还给了观众获得感
It was truly impressive.
非常的精彩
However, the affirmative side didn’t delve much into these two areas.
而正方呢在这两个战战场上琢磨不多
They played it a bit thin.
打的比较薄
I thought the affirmative side could have expanded on efficiency within this system.
本来我觉得正方在这个体系上是可以从效率
Or they could have delved into the significance of cooperation.
或者可以从合作的意义上啊去展开说说的
But Professor Zhang’s argument was a bit too lean.
但就是我说的这个张老师瘦身瘦的有点过
So, it was hard to build on the value afterward.
那么后面再递价值就有点立不住了
I found that a bit disappointing.
这一点我觉得稍微有点可惜
Then, in the previous round, both sides didn’t really delve into some of the finer points of attack and defense.
然后呢刚才这一场双方在一些比较细的攻防上
The technical aspects of the debate, I mean.
技术性的攻防啊
Actually, no one really expanded on them much.
其实大家都没有怎么展开的啊
For instance, we could break down the topic, right?
比如说我们可以去拆这个辩题对吧
The very detailed concepts and definitions.
很细致的概念和定义
Like, under what specific circumstances
类似于到底是在怎样的情况下
would this issue even come up? Would it even be raised? Because in most cases, we all know that If the boss occasionally makes some minor and silly decisions as long as they're not harmful most professionals can understand rarely would someone say I’m going to oppose everything the boss does
这个问题才会被抛出来 才会被提出来 因为一般情况下 我们都知道 如果老板偶尔有一些小的愚蠢决策 无伤大雅的话 职场人都能理解 很很少有人说我要反对一切老板啊
a role that seems foolish
看上去愚蠢的角色
or a role that rubs me the wrong way
或者我看不顺眼的角色
people wouldn’t act like that
大家不会这样的
So when does this issue come up?
那么什么时候这个问题被提出来呢
The affirmative side could argue whether the company culture is too casual
正方可以说是不是这个公司文化太随意了
making it impossible to enforce work arrangements
工作安排根本执行不下去呢
The opposing side can also say that it isn't so.
反方也可以说是不是啊
It's really because the boss is too foolish.
实在老板太愚蠢了
There are too many foolish characters.
愚蠢角色太多了
That's why this issue exists.
这个问题才存在呢
For example, what does compliance mean?
还比如说顺从是什么意思
Does compliance mean endless compromise?
顺从是不是意味着无限的妥协呢
Does it necessarily mean servile obedience?
是不是一定是近乎于奴隶式的服从呢
And opposition, does it necessarily mean being a troublemaker?
嗯反对呢是不是一定是刺儿头式的反对呢
Who, after all, defines foolishness?
还有愚蠢到底是谁定义的
Is there really someone with the authority to make such a decision?
是不是真的有人有权做出一个决策
Is it really the definition of foolishness?
到底是不是愚蠢的定义呢
And does a foolish decision mean it's foolish at the moment?
还有就是愚蠢决策是说当前愚蠢
Or is it foolish only when viewed with hindsight?
还是说我们开了上帝视角之后愚蠢
These questions weren't thoroughly debated by either side.
这些问题双方并没有拉扯得很细致
But I don't think this is a flaw.
但是我觉得这并不是缺点
Anyway, I think it was a very engaging debate just now. It gave me a lot of inspiration. So thank you, Professor Zhang and Professor Yu. Thank you, Professor Jiang. Thank you very much indeed. Your remarks have also brought us a lot of inspiration. I think there's a saying that goes:
总之我觉得刚才是非常精彩的一场辩论 给了我很多启发 那么谢谢张老师和于老师 谢谢蒋老师 非常非常感谢您 您的发言也带给我们非常多的启发啊 我想呢有句话叫做
Everyone is an expert in their own problems.
每个人都是自己问题的专家
The foolish decisions made by the bosses we encounter can vary greatly in their foolishness.
每个人遇到的老板做的愚蠢决策究竟有多愚蠢
They come in all sorts and sizes.
都是各式各样长得不一样的
The challenges we each face are unique in their own way.
我们每个人遇到的困境长得不一样
So it's only natural that some people might feel, hey,
所以自然而然的有些人就先天的觉得诶
I should just comply.
我就应该是顺从
Or I should resist.
或者就应该是反抗
This is also why debates can continue to thrive.
这也是为什么辩论可以持续进行下去的原因
We all have our own stories to tell.
我们每个人都有自己的话要说
So I really encourage everyone to share.
所以我也非常鼓励大家
Feel free to write about the foolish bosses you've encountered
到时候把自己遇到的愚蠢老板
The boss's foolish character is written in the comments section.
老板的愚蠢角色写在评论区里面
Let's broaden our horizons.
让我们大开眼界
You can also share this video with your colleagues.
也可以把这个视频发给你的同事
to improve your working relationships.
以增进同事关系
You can even forward this video to your boss.
更可以把这个视频转发给你的老板
to subtly convey some messages.
隐晦地表达一些什么东西
Thank you all for your participation.
非常感谢所有朋友们的参与